Now we'll look at another AWS security service called as AWS Identity and Access Management.
In short, it's called as IAM. Now, AWS IM service securely controls access to AWS resources.
When we say AWS resources, we mean any AWS servers such as S3, EC2, DynamoDB, and so on.
Now, IAM service focuses on two areas. One, it authenticates the user and that could be through
AWS console with username, password, or programmatically through secret key and access key.
And the second thing it focuses on is authorization. What is the level of permission
that the authenticated user has? Does it have access to all the services or does it have access
to, let's say, only one service S3 bucket? Now, within AWS IM, there are three key concepts
that you need to know. One is the AWS IM users and groups. IAM rules, IAM policies, and permissions.
Now, let's take a look at IAM users and groups. So, IAM users are assigned to workforce users.
Users are created for individuals who need access to AWS services. So, let's say here,
IAM Rahul and IAM a server admin. So, if I need to access this EC2 instance or this S3 bucket,
we'll need to create an IAM user who will have access to these servers. Next, let's say we have
Joe who is the billing admin. So, he will need access to the billing console. So, we'll create
a user within the identity and access management service for Joe who will have access to the
to the billing service. So, that is what IAM user is used for. So, once you have created the IAM user,
then you will need to attach policy and we'll get to what are policies. But just think about
policies as permission level. So, whether Rahul needs access to only EC2 instance S3 or both of them,
it will give it the right permission level. Then, IAM users and groups are sometimes called
as identities with long-term credentials and what that means is. Now, let's say IAM Rahul,
the server admin. So, I will get a user name and password if I want to access the AWS account.
So, it will be a long long-term credential. So, it can be there for weeks, months,
or till the time I am in the project. And as we will see later, there are also some temporary
security credentials. But IAM user and groups provide long-term credentials. So, now let's
understand what groups mean. Now, within the organization, you could have a lot of different team
members who will act as server admins. So, rather than creating multiple users and giving them
similar permissions, you could create a group, maybe you create a server admin group,
and then just add users to that group. So, let me just quickly show you. I am on the AWS
console. So, let me just surf for IAM. And here I am. So, now, I am on the identity and
access management service. So, I can just on the left-hand side, just click on users, create user,
let me just say Rahu, underscore admin. So, I will just click on next. Okay, this name already
exists. So, let me just say Rahu, underscore admin 1, 2, 3. I will just click on next.
Then I have to attach permissions. So, I can either add user to the group or copy permissions
or attach policies directly. So, I will just click on attach policies directly. And you can see
there are a lot of different pre-built AWS managed policies here. You can see AWS managed.
So, if I want admin access or if I want access to a particular service. So, if I just click on
this admin access. So, it will show you all the permissions provided to this particular policy.
And you can see it has access to all these services and it has full access. You can see it access
level. So, let me just go back. Okay, now let me just say I want to give it admin access. So,
I will just click on this admin access. And then I will just click next. And then I can just click
on create user. So, you can see it has created the user successfully. So, I can just click on
view user. And you can see the user name Rahu, admin 1, 2, 3. And then you can see under the
permission policies, I have given it administrative access. So, similarly you can click on user
group, I can just click on create group. And then just give it a group name here. And then attach
policies like we had done for the user. And then just click on create user group. And then we can
add the users within this user group. Now, the next concept within IM is IM roles. So, unlike the
users where you will have the credentials to access the console or programmatically access
various services, IM role is assumed by an AWS service or an application. Now, let us
understand what that means. So, let us say we have this EC2 instance. And this is the example
we had discussed earlier, we said it acts as a web server and it is going to fetch the images
from the S3 bucket. Now, by default, no AWS service has access to another service. And that is
important because let us say if this EC2 instance had access to all the S3 buckets within your account,
then in some of the S3 buckets you might be storing confidential information. So, someone
let us say Rahul who has access to this EC2 instance can go and fetch data from that S3 bucket.
So, that is why every time you are creating an application, you need to create a role for this
EC2 instance which allows it access to maybe S3 bucket or if it needs to access, maybe an RDS
database or any other service. So, in most occasions when you want to provide access to an AWS
service like EC2, S3 and so on to another service, then it is used something known as IM role.
So, you create an IM role just like the user and then you attach a set of permissions
which allows it access to another AWS service. And this is sometimes called as temporary
security credentials because the access that service has is valid only for limited duration,
maybe R or a couple of hours. So, hopefully it is clear, I am users and groups are used for work
for users, IM roles are used for AWS services and applications. But please note in very rare
circumstances when you are providing cross account access, which means let us say you have 10
accounts with no organization and one of the users or workforce users has access to a particular
account. But let us say he needs to access the billing details of the second account.
In that scenario, you will attach an IM role to this user but that is a very rare scenario.
In most scenarios, you can assume if it is an individual or a human, you can create an IM
user or group for them, if it is an AWS service or an application, then you can create an
IM role with the exception of cross account access, then we have the IM permission and policies.
So, permissions define which actions are allowed or denied. So, let us say there is an
AWS service that is trying to access this S3 bucket. So, it can have read-only access,
create access, delete access or all three. So, the permissions define what actions are allowed or
denied. And then we have the IM policy, it is basically a document that defines the permissions
that can be granted to an IM role or IM user and group. So, what you essentially do is,
once you create either an IM user, group or a role, you attach the policies to the IM role
or IM group and user. That is pretty much it from this lecture. I will see you in the next
lecture. Thank you.